<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first dish at the Wil-shire feast, Novemb. 9, 1654, or, A sermon preached at Laurence Jury to those that there offered their peace-offerings, and went thence to dine at Merchant-Taylors-Hall by Samuel Annesley ...</title>
            <author>Annesley, Samuel, 1620?-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25468</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3229</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11991069</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11991069</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52031</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25468)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52031)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 557:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first dish at the Wil-shire feast, Novemb. 9, 1654, or, A sermon preached at Laurence Jury to those that there offered their peace-offerings, and went thence to dine at Merchant-Taylors-Hall by Samuel Annesley ...</title>
                  <author>Annesley, Samuel, 1620?-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 19 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E.T. for Nathanael Webb and William Grantham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Chronicles, 1st, XXII, 32 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52031:1"/>
            <p>THE FIRST DISH AT THE <hi>WIL-SHIRE FEAST,</hi> NOVEMB. 9. 1654. OR, A SERMON Preached at LAURENCE JURY to thoſe that there offered their Peace-offerings, and went thence to dine at MARCHANT-TAYLORS-HALL. By SAMUEL ANNESLEY L.L.D. Miniſter of the Goſpel, at John Evangeliſts London.</p>
            <q>If by any means I may provoke to Emulation them which are my fleſh, and might ſave ſome of them,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 11.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>God is able to make all Grace abound towards you, that ye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes have all ſufficiencie in all things, may abound to every good Worke,
<bibl>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 9.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E.T.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Webb</hi> and <hi>William Grantham</hi> at the Black Beare in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1655.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52031:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52031:2"/>
            <head>To the Gentlemen, and Others of <hi>Wil-ſhire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the extreame ſhortnes of time, for the compoſing of this Sermon, did not fright me from preaching it; ſo neither did the extreame importunity of friends, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure me to print it. Conſcience of duty makes me dare not to refuſe my Maſters worke: And hopes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking others to Emulation <hi>[while ſeveral Counties are in the humour of feaſting]</hi> doth enforce the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to publique view. I am not onely aſhamed, but griev'd to heare of many County-feaſts, but—nothing more.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe, there's a Tang of indignation (in this <hi>crambe bis cocta</hi>) this muſhroome againe ſet upon the table: the trouble begun in that you did no more for your County, and it hath been ſince height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that others doe not ſo much for theirs. You have the honour to give the Nation a Precedent, pray ſcorn
<pb facs="tcp:52031:3"/>to be outſtript by any. Other Counties may ſee, how eaſily they may doe themſelves good; I hope they will ſcorne you ſhould be ſingular. Hath not this put ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Counties upon feaſting? ſuch a County feaſts, and why ſhould not wee? will it not better follow? ſuch a County invited Chriſt to their feaſt, and why ſhould not we? O that I could put every County into a flame of contention! but tis onely, who ſhould doe moſt for the ſuppreſſing of wickedneſſe; removing of ignorance: promoting of godlineſſe. And for your County, that I may warrantably invert my Text, <hi>The men of Wil-ſhire, which were men that had underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Times, to know what England ought to do, about five hundred of them met at a Feaſt, and all their brethren are willing to further their pious Projects.</hi> This is the unfeigned deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant for Jeſus ſake, SAMUEL ANNESLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52031:3"/>
            <head>THE FIRST DISH AT THE WILL-SHIRE FEAST, NOVEM. 9. 1654.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 CHRON. 12.32.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And of the children of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> which were men that had under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Times, to know what <hi>Iſrael</hi> ought to do: the heads of them were two hundred, and all their brethren were at their commandment.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Forbear a Preface, becauſe I have ſo much work in the Text. To improve time at the firſt, that we may not want it at the laſt, I ſhall fall directly upon the words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And of the children of</hi> Iſſachar, <hi>which were men that had underſtanding of the times, to know, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In an hiſtorical relation, you expect no other choice of words, then only fit expreſſions, neither will a narrative well endure a garniſh; for many times, while the ſtory is trim'd, the truth is ſmother'd: yet in ſome caſes, the higheſt ſtrains of Rhetorical elegance, can but ſufficiently adorn noble Truth.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:52031:4"/>
            <p>And what will you ſay to this Text? here is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary emphatical Hebraiſme, and an ordinary Metanymie in one ſentence, and a ſignificant Trajection in the next, but I will ſhew you, not tell you what there is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And of the children of Iſſachar]</hi> a quiet midling tribe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the head nor the tail. In the ſolemn and prophetical bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Tribes, both by <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> there's not much good promiſed to them, and therefore the more obſervable to read ſuch things of them. They</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Were men that had underſtanding of the times]</hi> here's their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, and 'tis excellently expreſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing underſtanding to the times:</hi> the word <hi>[knowing]</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects the mind in way of apprehenſion: the word <hi>[under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding]</hi> reſpects the mind in way of conſideration, when the mind doth accurately diſcern, and judge of things. And the word <hi>[times] lagnittim,</hi> the 70. well renders <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the occaſion of time,</hi> and ther's a Metanymie of the adjunct, time being put for the things done in time, <hi>q. d.</hi> they had given themſelves much to obſerve ſeaſons, wherein matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were meeteſt to be done, and by obſerving the occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of affaires, they got much experience, and thereby much wiſdome. And this their underſtanding was not for meer ſpeculation, but</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To know what Iſrael ought to do]</hi> (or if you admit of a traje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction) <hi>that Iſrael might know what to do.</hi> They inſtructed them that were any way under them, or that came to them for advice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Heads of them were</hi> 200.] the diviſion of <hi>Canaan</hi> unto the ſeveral Tribes, is not altogether unlike the diviſion of our and into Shires. And the officers of their particular Tribes, do ſomewhat reſemble our Sheriffe, Juſtices of the Peace, Mayors, Bayliffes, Conſtables, and other Officers of Shires, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Burroughs, Hundreds, and Pariſhes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all their brethren were at their commandment] gnal pihem ſuper os eorum,</hi> becauſe the command proceeds from the mouth. Their prudence was ſo highly eſteemed, that every one was willing to do what they adviſed. In ſhort, here were 200. of the children of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> men that had underſtanding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52031:4"/>of the times, that knew and conſidered what was ſeaſonable to be done, and all their brethren were willing to follow their advice. Whence you may learn this Doctrine</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That where ſome few hundreds of countreymen meet, that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the duty of the times, they may lead their whole countrey along with them, for their general good.</hi> Here were two hundred of the tribe of <hi>Iſſachar</hi> met together at <hi>Hebron,</hi> then the chief City of the Nation, and they met at a Feaſt of their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding, for <hi>verſ.</hi> 40. <hi>The men of</hi> Iſſachar—<hi>brought bread,—meat, meal, cakes of figs, and bunches of raiſins, and wine, and oyle, and oxen, and ſheep abundantly: for there was joy in</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>They manage the proper duty of the times with ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and diſcretion, that all the countrey whence they came, are willing to do what they adviſe them.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine is ſo natural, I need not call in Scriptures to avouch it. Take one that will do more then prove it, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.16.22. one wiſe woman of the City went unto all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in her wiſdom, and perſwades them to what preſerves them from deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. Wherein doth this underſtanding conſiſt? I will keep within the very words of the text, and what they plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly import.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. In a true knowledge and apprehenſion of things, as they are in their own nature. To know the nature of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine command, and the nature of a chriſtian duty. And to ſpeak plainly in a word, ſuch knowledge you will never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to, but by the Scripture. I remember <hi>Auguſtin</hi> cloſeth his commendation of Scripture thus; <hi>That whatſoever a man hath learned,</hi> extra Scripturam, <hi>if it be hurtfull, there 'tis condemned; if it be profitable, there 'tis found. There you ſhall abundantly find all thoſe things, which you can profitably learn elſewhere, and thoſe things which you can learn no where elſe, are there taught with wonderful height, yet condeſcention.</hi> Prov. 3.4. <hi>Forget not the Law, keep the Commandement, ſo ſhalt thou have good underſtanding in the ſight of God and man. [Good underſtanding]</hi> or good ſucceſs, the Hebrew word ſignifies both, and there is good reaſon why it ſhould, becauſe of the near dependance of the things themſelves: Good underſtanding, doth beget good ſucceſſe.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52031:5"/>
            <p n="2">2. This underſtanding conſiſts in a due conſideration of their duty. I dare appeal to your own conſciences, whether conſideration be not a principall ingredient in the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all graces. How come perſons to repent of ſin? when do they ſet themſelves againſt ſin? when they <hi>conſider</hi> the evill of it, and the danger they are expoſed to, by it. When do perſons look after Chriſt, but when they <hi>conſider</hi> the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of him, and that they are undone without him, that he invites them to come, and 'tis beſt to take his invitation? How come men to get this practical wiſdome, this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the text, but by enquiring what is their duty, and <hi>conſidering</hi> the fit circumſtances of performing it? <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, (<hi>Iob</hi> 23.15.) <hi>when I conſider, I am afraid. q.d.</hi> When I weigh in my mind all Gods proceedings with me, I am afraid. When conſcience is aſleep, conſideration will awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it; <hi>men could never run ſo madly into ſin, were they not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Diligence is requiſite to this underſtanding. This is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied in both the other; you will never get a right knowledge of things, without a diligent ſearching after knowledge: you will never conſider rightly of things without a diligent fixing of your hearts upon your duty. <hi>The diligent hand</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) <hi>makes rich,</hi> rich in grace, rich in all good works; a lazie chriſtian is alwayes a beggatly chriſtian. You know one of the firſt curſes that God denounced againſt man, was, <hi>in the ſweat of thy brow, thou ſhalt eat thy bread.</hi> Now though all cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be taken away by Chriſt, yet this lies ſtill as a a croſs in the way of a chriſtian, that even in ſpirituals, he cannot earn his bread, he can never get, nor improve any grace without ſweating for it. Gods free gift doth not hinder, but further and encourage labour and diligence. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.10. <hi>whatſoever thy hand findeth to do do it with all thy might: for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wiſdom in the grave, whither thou goeſt.</hi> This brings to the ſecond Quaere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. What underſtanding ought we to have of the times?</p>
            <p>I muſt intreat you to be ſerious in the anſwer to this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, for it cannot but thwart the common practice of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52031:5"/>generality of men. This underſtanding of the times con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in theſe three things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. In the underſtanding of the general duties of all times: There are ſome duties which run through the whole courſe of our lives; we ought to live alwayes in the fear of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.30. <hi>God calls upon all men every where to repent:</hi> we ought alwayes to make Religion our buſineſſe, to do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to Gods diſhonour, but to put forth our ſelves to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to walk acceptably before him; to bind our ſelves to our good behaviour: Yet do not miſtake, as if the ſtrongeſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements to be wholly for God, had any the leaſt bondage in them; but I would have Religion to be like the marriage bond, That as there is none more ſtrong, ſo there is none more deſireable, more comfortable. I would have you al to entertain Religion with ſomething ſutable to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Ark, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.5. <hi>When the Ark of the Covenant of the Lord came into the Camp, all</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhouted with a great ſhout, ſo that the earth rang again:</hi> ſo that the enemies of holineſſe may cry out, <hi>Woe unto us, woe unto us,</hi> who can deliver us out of the hand of this mighty God, who will ſmite prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with all manner of plagues?</p>
            <p>And another general duty of all times, is to be profitable unto others: to do what we poſſibly can to promote Religion in the world. The Apo. in <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.12, 13. compares the collective body of chriſtians to the natural body of an infant, and Chriſt to the ſoul; as the child grows in all the parts of the body, ſo the ſoul puts forth it ſelf in all rational operations. Now every member grows not out of ſelf-intereſt, but common intereſt, and Chriſt communicates of his ſpirit according to ſuch growth; only here's the diſſimilitude: let a child grow never ſo faſt, yet the growth doth not make any addition of new members unto the body, there's not ſo much as a finger, or a toe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for all the growth: but now Religion ſpreads it ſelf like l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, communicates it ſelf unto thoſe that are yet unlevened. Ther's addition of members in the myſtical body of Chriſt. And there is not any gracious ſoul, but can heartily joyn with <hi>Paul</hi> in his wiſh for <hi>Agrippa.</hi> Acts 26.29. <hi>I would to God, that not only thou, but alſo all that hear me this day were both almoſt, and altogether ſuch as I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:52031:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, The underſtanding of the times conſiſteth in the underſtanding of the particular duties of ſpeciall times, every ſeaſon of a mans life brings 'its particular duties along with it. Remember thy Creatour in the daies of thy youth: doe not ſpend the morning of your life in vanitie, ſo let young men improve their ſtrength, and old men their experiences for God, and the good of others. But the Text fits us with two adjuncts of time very conſiderable.</p>
            <p>Firſt, they were times of diviſion, alteration and changes: and what are ours? they had been long harraſt with civill war, between <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> and they were yet unſettled; now at ſuch a time the ſons of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> many of them ſhepheards, moſt of them plaine country-men. Theſe knew what to doe, this ſhews their wiſdome. Goe you, and doe likewiſe. But what ſhall we doe? I will tell you what, and give you a preſident for it. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. <hi>for ſo is the will of God, that with well doing, ye may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men,</hi> there's your duty. <hi>Daniel</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>Then the Preſidents and Princes ſought to find occaſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Daniel <hi>concerning the Kingdome, but they could find none occaſion, nor fault: for as much as he was faithfull, neither was there any error or fault found in him. Then ſaid theſe men, we ſhall not find any occaſion againſt this</hi> Daniel, <hi>except we find it againſt him, concerning the law of his God.</hi> There's your preſident. Obſerve the time of it, 'twas when <hi>Darius</hi> had broken the head of gold, the Babylonian monarchy, and now <hi>Daniel</hi> is againe gracious in court, and prefer'd in office above all the enemies of the church. Theſe could find <hi>[no occaſion]</hi> no matter of accuſation, nor colour of ſuſpition of unfaithfulnes <hi>[neither was there any error]</hi> his many, mighty, envious, ſubtill enemies deſpaired to find him faulty, or colourably faulty in the management of ſo great affairs, in ſo tickle times <hi>[except we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it againſt him concerning the law of his God]</hi> they muſt proceed to out-rage againſt God himſelfe, or they can do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt him. In a word then; walke ſo exactly, that your very enemies may have nothing againſt you, and if the world uſe you like it ſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.12. <hi>rejoyce, and be exceeding glad for great is your reward in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52031:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, they were times of opportunities for doing good: and ſo are ours. 'Tis confeſt all times have ſomthing pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar in them to exerciſe the graces of the godly: and there will never want ſnares to entangle thoſe that are godly, but let us not for any evill that we feel or feare, neglect the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities of doing that good which we may—what oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities you have, I ſhall ſhew you in the application.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The third thing wherein the right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the times conſiſts, is in prudently obſerving the fit ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the performing of all duties. Every thing is beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in its ſeaſon: and it is conſiderable, God never calls to any worke, but he gives a fit ſeaſon for the doing of it. <hi>I muſt work, ſaith Chriſt while it is day, the night cometh when no man can worke.</hi> Eccleſ. 8.6. <hi>Becauſe to every purpoſe there is time and judgement: therefore the miſery of man is great upon him.</hi> Every enterpriſe hath its proper ſeaſon, and peculiar manner of acting, upon which narrow point the ſucceſſe of ſuch under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings doth depend, and this cannot without wiſdome be duely obſerved. There's a word uſed. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>helpeth our infirmities</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, lifts over againſt us; 'tis a metaphor taken from two mens lifting at a logg, which one man cannot move; now the ſpirit of God lifts at the heavier end; if we lift with him, we may go thorough with our duty, but if we loſe the ſeaſon of his help, all our endeavours may come to nothing. For if that ſeaſon which God affordeth us for buſineſſe be loſt, 'tis probably loſt irrecoverably. I once ſaw a ſhip ſtrike upon the Goodwin ſands, but the tide com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, and help being at hand juſt in the nicke of time, it came off ſafe, whereas had it beene let alone a little till ebbing wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it had beene loſt irrecoverably: Doe but time your buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and you ſayle before the wind, looſe your opportunity, and you drive as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did in the red ſea, when his chariet-wheeles were taken off. I cannot better expreſſe this, thereby turning you to Chriſts owne words, which he uttered with tears over the once holy city, which is now a ruinous heape. <hi>Luke.</hi> 19.41, 42. <hi>when he was come neare, he beheld the city and wept over it, ſaying, if thou hadſt known, even thou, at leaſt in this thy day, the things which belong unto thy peaco! but now they are hid from thine eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:52031:7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 3. How is it likely that a few underſtanding men may probably ingage all their country-men to performe the duties of the times they live in. I ſhall only name a two fold ground.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> 1. Men know the ſtate of their owne country better then ſtrangers can, to ſpeake directly <hi>ad rem:</hi> here you are met from all parts of your country. Doe not you know the ſtate of your country better then ten times your number of any other men in the world? One can ſay, I was born in ſuch a place, where the Goſpel was never powerfully preacht in my time. Another can ſay, I live in a place, where profanenes doeth exceedingly abound. And a third can tell ſtories of the ranting, and licentiouſneſſe of apoſtate Chriſtians. Againe, you know the temper of your owne neighbours and country men, better then others can: you know in what places peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be incorrigible, and men muſt deale with them as with thornes, as <hi>David</hi> expreſſed it: you know where people are fickle and unſetled, that they muſt be ſtroakt into a good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ſound truth, or they will fly out, &amp; be worſe by means of bettering them. And</p>
            <p>Secondly, Men of the ſame country are intereſted in one anothers affections, which doth exceedingly fit them for the doing &amp; receiving of good: men will take that from a country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, a neighbour, a friend, which they will not from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Let me tell you plainly, you have carried your ſelves ill in the places of your abode, if you have not gotten ſome eſteeme and credit, more then in places where you are not knowne, that a reproofe or an admonition will come with authority from you. Men commonly love the places of their birth, and their country-men among whom they were bred, being more willing to doe for them then for others; and the places of our nativity and education doe challenge, and looke for ſomthing from us. This is deſervedly put into Sions la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, that of all the ſons ſhee brought up, there was none to comfort her. Now if God give you opportunity, will you not anſwer it? you read of <hi>Mordecai Eſter,</hi> 10.3. <hi>Morde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cai</hi> the Jew was great among the Jews, and accepted of the multitude of his brethren, ſeeking the wealth of his people, and ſpeaking peace to all his ſeed.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52031:7"/>
            <p>But I haſten to the application, and begin with an uſe of Reproofe, wherein if any ſhall thinke I am too keene, let them thinke withall, that I ſhall be glad to be miſtaken, in the ſins that I reprove, if you can plead for your country in any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, not guiltie. But if theſe ſins be among you, the two edged ſword had need to cut, and therefore I will not ſay, beare with me, but as <hi>Jothan</hi> to the Shechemites, <hi>Hearken unto me you men of Shechem, that God may hearken unto you:</hi> There are five ſins I ſhall reprove, and with the reproofe propoſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, that as I launch the ſore, I may apply a plaiſter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Profaneneſſe:</hi> Are there not with you, even with you, aye with us in this congregation, ſome profane <hi>Eſau's,</hi> that will hunt away their bleſſing, and game away their bleſſing, and ſweare away their bleſſing, and drinke away their bleſſing, that ſcorn preciſeneſſe, and hate reproofe? to ſuch as theſe, I am ſent with heavy tidings; I muſt tell you from a holy God, that when you can laugh no more at holineſſe, God will laugh for ever at your deſtruction: that when you have wearyed your ſelves in workes of darkeneſſe, you ſhall have your portion in everlaſting darkeneſſe; I remember a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of your owne country, 'tis of <hi>Roger</hi> Biſhop of Salisbury, that built Shirborne Caſtle, and the Caſtle of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſes</hi> (accounted once one of the goodlieſt Caſtles of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi>) when he was ready to die, 'tis reported, that <hi>inter mortis metum, et vitae tormenta, vivere noluerit, et mori neſcierit,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene feare of death, and torment of life, he would not live, and yet he knew not how to die. How ſoone may this be your caſe? remember <hi>Eſau</hi> Heb. 12.16.17. that profane perſon <hi>Eſau, who for one morſell of meat ſold his birthright, for you know how that afterward when he would have inherited the bleſſing, he was rejected, for he found no place of repentance, though he ſought, it carefully with teares.</hi> I hope better things of you, but pray then, doe what you can to ſtop the inundation of profaneneſſe in the places where you live, or have acquaintance. What's the remedie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Put downe the multitude of ale-houſes in your country.</hi> Theſe are the peſt-houſes of the nation: it were well if they were ſhut up, for thence the plague of profaneneſſe ſpreades all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52031:8"/>over the land: but I forbeare them at preſent, this being one of the projects wherewith I ſhall cloſe my ſermon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The ſecond ſin is <hi>errour,</hi> this is the cunning of the old ſerpent, that when he cannot keepe perſons, profane, he will drive them into the other extreame; if profaneneſſe ſtare men in the face, and looke dreadfully, then a ſmacke of religion, with a vigorous imbracing of ſome unſound opinion will ſet them in the higheſt forme of Chriſtianity preſently. O beloved, it is ſad to conſider, how this leproſie ſpreads, what more ordinary then for perſons when their conſciences are a little awakened, and thereby diſquieted by the word, to take the <hi>opium</hi> of ſome errour, and quiet all againe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Heretofore upon the preaching of the word, you ſhould have perſons <hi>pricked at the heart, and cry out, Men and brethren, what ſhall we doe to be ſaved?</hi> But now if ſtrictneſſe be preſſed, that's <hi>Legall;</hi> if repentance be urged, that is <hi>not fine enough;</hi> when poore ſoules are a little ſtartled by a rouzing ſermon, ſatan hath his emiſſaries to ſeize upon them, let them but liſt themſelves in ſuch a congregation, take up ſuch an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the worke is done, they are Saints preſently.</p>
            <p>The cure of this, is, get a godly Miniſter into your country, if you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not get a ſufficient number ſetled, yet you may procure ſome godly, learned, prudent Miniſters to preach up &amp; down in the country, from place to place, that there may not be a darke corner in the country. Be as vigilant for <hi>truth</hi> as ſatan is for <hi>errour:</hi> let not ſatan ſet up his flag, but indeavour [what in you lies] that the ſpirit of God may lift up a ſtandard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. You may probably meet with reproaches here, but goe on, feare not. When by <hi>Jeromes</hi> meanes ſome hereticks loſt their libertie of teaching their errour, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writes thus to him, <hi>I have alwaies honoured thee, but now much more, if my eſteeme be capable of addition. All that love the truth will reverence thee, and which is a greater glory, all hereticks deteſt thee.</hi> Gentlemen, I would recommend unto you <hi>Jehaſhaphats</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, He ſent <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> to preach in the cities of <hi>Judah,</hi> and his Princes accompanied them, to give countenance and incouragement to the deſigne, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 17.7, 8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the third ſin is <hi>formalitie in religion,</hi> which is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52031:8"/>elſe but a finely compoſed and well acted tragedie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> religion, a pageant of piety, a reſemblance of godlines. <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſpeaking of ſome kinde of Chriſtians, ſaith, They were but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and they had only <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them.</p>
            <p>And Chriſt calls them <hi>whited Sepulchres,</hi> they have religion written in capitall golden letters upon the outſide, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they are nothing but ſtinking rottenneſſe. O that you would deale plainely with your owne ſouies, is there any here, that ſerves God with a reſerve, that quarrells with ſcripture for requiring more ſtrictneſſe, then they are willing to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe? I remember it is given as one character of the <hi>Manachees,</hi> that they labour for nothing more, then <hi>not to find what they ſeeke.</hi> Is not this the character of ſome here? I am ſure it is of too many profeſſours that pretend to ſearch after the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of their dutie, but they are loath to find it: pretend they would ſeeke out their ſecret ſins, but they are loath to part with them.</p>
            <p>For the cure of this. Truly I am here almoſt at a ſtand, this diſeaſe is <hi>Ludibrium theologorum,</hi> theſe kinde of Chriſtians can doe by ſermons, as Mountebankes doe by poyſon, they are fore-armed, that they cannot worke upon them; let Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters ſay what they can, they will practiſe what they liſt: this diſeaſe is like the ſtone in the bladder, the remedies ſpend their ſtrength ere they come at the place affected: reproofe, and conviction, and counſell, have ſpent their ſtrength, before they can come neere their hearts, but I muſt attempt a cure. The only remedie I know, is a <hi>doſe of true repentance;</hi> this may ſet them right, and that I may ſet it on with efficacy, I will give you a ſcripture inſtance, what a cure repentance wrought, in a caſe as bad as this, <hi>(ſo farr as any ſin may be compared with formalitie</hi>) there were ſome hundreds of one tribe met together, and a ſad meeting it was, but it proved a good one at laſt, it is the tribe of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> I meane, who for their ſin were brought to 600 men only. <hi>Judges</hi> 20.47. in the dayes of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> there were 380000 fighting men of that tribe. The greateſt number of them in the plaines of <hi>Moab</hi> were but 45600, not the ſixth part of what they were after
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52031:9"/>their great blow, upon their repentance they mightily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, out of a ſmall handfull; ſin brings low, but God upon our ſerious repentance, can quickly increaſe us, and make our latter end better then our beginning.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, A fourth ſin is <hi>uſeleſneſſe:</hi> how many are there that are rather-like what <hi>Jacob</hi> foretold of <hi>Iſſachar,</hi> then what <hi>Ezra</hi> here records of them, <hi>that he is like an aſſe, couching downe betweene two burthens, becauſe reſt is good.</hi> Many men care not ſo they can but ſnug in quiet and rub out their time without trouble and danger; if they can do ſo, they take themſelves to be very wiſe men: as if men were ſent into the world, to have only ſuch a narrative made of them, as there is of ſome Judges of Iſrael; they had ſo many cities, ſo many children, and they rode upon ſo many aſſes, and that is all you read of them. So ſuch a man he got a great eſtate, and he matched his children very well, and perhaps when he is dead, you may hear of ſome charitable legacie in his <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> but not by his <hi>Will;</hi> thanke you death, or you ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have heard of any good at all, <hi>and but a little then.</hi> If this baſeneſſe be creeping upon any of you, for cure of it</p>
            <p>Take a holy revenge upon your ſelves, do you finde your hearts cling cloſe to the world, 'tis like the cleaving of a cold hand unto a hot fire-iron in extremitie of weather, 'tis ſome refreſhing at preſent, but it teares the fleſh off when removed. You cannot let your hands cleave to the world, but it will doe worſe then burne your fingers. It is a prettie paſſage (me thinkes) that I heard of a Gentleman as he rode by the way, an old man begged ſomething of him, and he gave him a groat, when he rode a little paſt, he bethought himſelfe, a groat, that might have ſerved 3 or 4, upon theſe thoughts he rode backe to the poore man, and demanded his groat, which when he returned him, he gave him a ſhilling, ſaying to himſelfe, <hi>now I am revenged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, The fifth ſin I ſhall reprove, is <hi>Temporizing,</hi> this is the underſtanding moſt men have of the times; they know how to make their advantage of the times, to turne with the times, and to ſerve the times: they can fawne upon the ſins of the times. O the baſe ſpiritedneſſe of the men of this generation!
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52031:9"/>that if they can but cringe themſelves into preferment, and get ſome fat gobbets of wealth, or bladder of honour, blown up with ſtinking breath like their own: they will venture the diſpleaſure of God, and what not! Do any of your conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces tell you, you are ſuch? let me adde this for conſcience to chew upon; you ſhall be filled with your own waies. You can complement with God, and give him good language, but nothing elſe, ſo God will give you good words again, but turn you off with, I know you not; or as Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Judas, Friend, wherefore art thou come? betrayeſt thou the ſon of man with a kiſſe? it were better for thee thou hadſt never been born.</hi> Can any of you kiſſe Chriſt, and betray him? bow the knee to him, and ſmite him upon the head? Friends, what do you think Religion is? do you think it is a meer juggle, a Blinde to make uſe of? a Servant to wait upon your deſignes? are theſe things becoming chriſtians? but I muſt forbear.</p>
            <p>For the cure of it. <hi>Be convinced of the vanity of the creature.</hi> Do but, ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> withdraw thy ſelf a little, ſuppoſe thy ſelf on the top of ſome mountain, where thou mighteſt ſafely ſee <hi>fluctuantis mundi turbines,</hi> the world in its proper colours, thou wouldſt pitie the world, and rather bleſſe God for thy being delivered from the ſnares of it, then deſire to have much of it. Alas poor rich man! thou doſt ſhift, and ſhuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle, and make ſhipwrack of faith, and conſcience, and all to get — what I pray you? nay, I know not what, all thou canſt poſſibly get, will not buy a plaiſter broad enough to lay upon thy wounded conſcience: this is directly croſse to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.15, 16. <hi>See then that you walk circumſpectly, not as fooles, but as wiſe, redeeming the time, becauſe the dayes are evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond uſe is of <hi>Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Be perſwaded every one of you to <hi>mind Religion ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</hi> You know Chriſt tells us, that towards the end of the world, the times ſhall be like thoſe before the floud, men ſhall be eating and drinking, &amp;c. but in this unlike them; for then one might have a temporal deliverance by the faith of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but now, <hi>two ſhall be in one houſe, the one ſhall be taken,</hi> (to glory) <hi>and the other left</hi> (to periſh) two ſhall be in one bed, the one ſhall be taken (into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome) the other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52031:10"/>ſhall be left (to the devils torments) a believing wife cannot then ſave an unbeleeving husband, a gracious father, cannot then ſave an ungracious child. Chriſtians, 'tis a <hi>perſonal refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> I would firſt urge you to. Begin with your own hearts, and with your own lives. Take up <hi>Job</hi>'s reſolution, <hi>My heart ſhall not reproach me as long as I live:</hi> when you hear a Sermon, let every man think he is ſpoken to, in particular. This is one reaſon why the Commandements are given in the ſecond perſon ſingular, Thou ſhalt have no other Gods before me, &amp;c. every man is to applie them unto himſelfe, as if God ſpake to him by name. This is it that loſeth ſo many Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, aye, and ſo many ſouls to, <hi>viz.</hi> the want of perſonal application. O that I could therefore ſpeak to you all, as if I were ſpeaking but to one man. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.12. <hi>Every one of us muſt give account of himſelf to God:</hi> therefore 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.11. <hi>I exhort and charge every one of you (as a father doth his children) that ye would walk worthy of God, who calls you unto his Kingdom and Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Set up the <hi>Power of godlineſſe in your families:</hi> as ever you would have a part in <hi>Abrahams</hi> bleſſing, take part in his worke, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18, 19. <hi>I know him that he will command his children, and his houſhold after him, and they ſhall keepe the way of the Lord.</hi> He had as big a family to inſtruct as any of you: there were above three hundred in it, able to beare armes. But I will give you an inſtance beyond his, and 'tis of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> pray obſerve it, for the world can never match it. He had a thouſand wives, and could give an account (a true one, though a ſad one) of every one of their ſouls, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.28. And for the number of his ſervants, 'tis not eaſie to gueſſe the quantitie: how many ſervants muſt every one of his wives have? he had ſeven hundred wives which were Princeſſes, their retinue was certainly great; he had forty thouſand ſtalls of horſes for his charets: Judge hereby what a world of ſervants there muſt be belonging to his Court. You read his daiely proviſion, that ſhews the greatneſſe of his family. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4.22, 23. <hi>And Solomous proviſion for one day was thirty meaſures of fine flowre, and threeſcore meaſures of meale</hi> (that is three hundred buſhells of flowre, and ſix hundred buſhells of meale) <hi>ten fat oxen, and twenty oxen out of the paſture, and an
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52031:10"/>hundred ſheepe, beſides harts, and roe-bucks, and fallow-deere, and fatted fowl:</hi> and yet his family, though ſo great, was ſo well ordered that, (1 <hi>King.</hi> 10.15.) the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> was ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to ſee it, nay more, his ſervants were ſo ſeaſoned with Religion, that about five hundred yeares after their children are in a ſpeciall manner recorded by the ſpirit of God, to be the moſt eminent of their times for Religion. <hi>Ezra.</hi> 2.58. <hi>The children of Solomons ſervants, were three hundred ninety and two:</hi> they are with the forwardeſt to enjoy freedome of Gods worſhip, and though others ſhrunke from their firſt ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo did not they; not a man of them, <hi>Nehem.</hi> 7.60. <hi>The children of Solomons ſervants were three hundred ninety and two.</hi> This cannot but ſhame us, that have ſo few to take care of, and yet take ſo little care of them. The Lord ſet it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our hearts.</p>
            <p>Thirdly. Combine together to <hi>advance Religion in your County.</hi> You know what God commanded his people to do for the land of their captivitie, where they were in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſlavery. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 29.7. <hi>Seek the peace of the City, whither I have cauſed you to be carried away captives, and pray unto the Lord for it: for in the peace thereof ſhall you have peace.</hi> What then ſhould you do for the place of your Nativity? Chriſt takes it for granted, that in <hi>Nazareth,</hi> where he had been brought up, <hi>They will ſurely uſe this Proverb, Phyſitian heal thy ſelf, whatſoever we have heard done in</hi> Capernaum, <hi>do alſo here in thy own countrey;</hi> and 'twas their oppoſition to the Goſpel, that hindred him from anſwering their expectation. Friends, I hope that oppoſition to the Goſpel will not hinder you, but that every one will be willing to do his utmoſt for your own Countie. It is eaſie to heape up inſtances in all hiſtories, what good Patriots have done for their countrie, but I forbear; and will only urge a raritie of your Countie: the like whereof, I do not remember that ever I heard or read: I mean that Cathedral which was longer in building then the Jewes Temple; for it was above fifty years in building: and do you not think the Founders did intend, by proportioning the doors to the moneths, and the windows to the daies, and the pillars to the houres of the year, that you ſhould learn this inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52031:11"/>
               <hi>Not a moneth, nay, not a day, nay, not an hour ſhould be let paſſe without ſomething of Religion?</hi> And what may you now do for promoting Religion in your County? what may you not do, if you will ſet to it in good earneſt?</p>
            <p>You know in our conſtitution of Parliaments, we have the members choſen from every County, and though ſome Counties have but a very few, yet their County expects good from them. Might we ſuppoſe now all the members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to be choſen out of one County, and that Parliament ſo conſtituted, to be the <hi>ſupreame Authority.</hi> O what would all thoſe men do for that County? why Friends, I may in ſome ſort call you <hi>the VVil-ſhire Parliament,</hi> and I dare bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay, if you will manage your buſineſſe wiſely, you may car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the projects I ſhall propoſe, with as good ſucceſſe, as if you had Parliamentary Authority to back them: and you may raiſe ſufficient money by voluntary contribution, as if you had power to lay a taxe; and I dare ſay, 'twill be paid more willingly. Me thinks by this time your Attention asks me, <hi>what would you have us to do?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall name three projects, which I ſhall but name, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more chargeable then the preſent times will bear.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To ſet up the light of the Goſpel in all the dark pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your Countie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To raiſe a ſtock to ſet the poor on work, this ſtock when once raiſed, a ſmall matter would continue it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To maintain ſome poor Schollars, for ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, at the Univerſity. If you will but think of theſe things, I may ſpare my labour in telling you the uſe of them. But I leave theſe; if any will but brood them between this and your next meeting, by that time theſe projects may be hatcht.</p>
            <p>At preſent, there are three things I ſhall crave leave to urge, as being more feaſible then the former. The firſt will ſave many extravagant expences. The ſecond may be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much charge, and the third is reſolved upon already by ſome, and I doubt not but will be embraced by all.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, put down all your <hi>wicked Alehouſes,</hi> if you have any mind to be rid of prophaneneſs, put down your <hi>baſe Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes.</hi> Theſe are the <hi>Devils Nurſeries,</hi> where his children are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52031:11"/>inſtructed in the myſteries of iniquitie. There it is men har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den themſelves againſt the Goſpel; and ſteep them ſelves, as if they would fain make themſelves like ſobby logges, of which the fire can have no power: but they are miſtaken in the nature of hell-fire, for though the Sea ſhould emptie it ſelf into the bottomleſs pit, 't would be as water upon lime, make it burn more fiercely. But there's not a drop of water to cool that tongue, that upon the <hi>Ale-bench</hi> ſets it ſelf againſt heaven.</p>
            <p>Could I perſwade you but to ſuppreſs <hi>Tippling,</hi> I ſhould not doubt but prophaneneſs would receive its mortal wound. But I muſt adde, Thoſe that undertake this buſineſs, muſt arme themſelves with patience, and reſolution, and manage it pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently; otherwiſe they will do more hurt, then good.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſet up pettie Schools in every Pariſh, or in every other Pariſh, to teach children to read, and let them be cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed every week. This though it may ſeem a difficult work, yet if you would all of you, according to your ſeveral relations, to ſeveral parts of the County, endeavour it: the work would be done ſpeedily, as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaid of the building of the wall of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> when every one took his part, and had a mind to the work (<hi>Nehem.</hi> 3. throughout.)</p>
            <p>How many poor people may hereby come to knowledge? many whole families in the countrey have not any one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in them that can read: how can theſe learn any thing? how can theſe ſanctifie a Sabbath? could their children but read, and were their children but taught the principles of chriſtian Religion, it might be a more ſpreading good then you are aware of: and <hi>one ten pounds would buy above two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Catechiſmes, which would yield a pretty handſome diſtribution to every Pariſh in your County.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My third project is contrived to my hand, <hi>viz.</hi> the ſetting up of ſome weekly Lectures in places moſt deſtitute of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. Now it is not onely propoſed, but reſolved by the <hi>Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> to ſet up two weekly Lectures for the year next enſuing, the one at <hi>Trubridge,</hi> the other at <hi>Calne,</hi> upon their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket daies, and to allow five and twentie pounds to each of thoſe two, godlie, able, and faithful Miniſters, whom they will forthwith employ to preach there: and if your bountiful
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52031:12"/>contribution ſhal exceed that ſum, the overplus ſhal be laid out, for the redeeming ſome of your countrey-men out of priſon.</p>
            <p>And now I have propoſed theſe things, I am ready to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, you will not need arguments to perſwade their enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. I can ſcarce think of any thing to be objected againſt them. 'Tis true, carnal reaſon may ſay, theſe kind of projects will ſpoile your meeting, for when you intend a meeting for the continuation of friendſhip, and ſhall be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon, to the picking of your purſes; who will meet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time? if carnal reaſon make this objection, I hope Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is well able to make an anſwer to it. 'Tis better never to meet, then meerly <hi>to eat, and drink, and riſe up to play:</hi> may you not expect, <hi>that while the meat is yet between your teeth, the wrath of God may fall upon you:</hi> or at leaſt, that <hi>God may ſend leanneſs into your ſoules.</hi> You know how Chriſt managed a great feſtival, <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.37, 38, 39. <hi>In that great day of the Feaſt, Ieſus ſtood, and cried, ſaying, If any man thirſt, let him come unto me, and drink, He that believeth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water; this ſpake he of the Spirit, which they that believe on him ſhould receive.</hi> O do what you may, to bring ſin-ſick ſoules unto Chriſt: to lay them under the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the Spirit of grace: and to ſtop up ſinners way with thornes. <hi>Ierom</hi> affirmes that this was <hi>Iſſachars</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the times; they were <hi>(inter alia) doctores ad feſtivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates,</hi> their excellency lay in giving directions about Religious feaſts; Though he may be miſtaken in the interpretation of the Text, I am ſure you will not be miſtaken in the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Text, if you Religiouſly and induſtriouſly ſet your ſelves <hi>[at this your Feaſt]</hi> to doe your country ſome reall ſpirituall good.</p>
            <p>But alas, 'tis not to be hoped that you ſhould all be unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in ſo good a deſign, there are but few will be drawn in to ſuch an undertaking, I will grant this. But becauſe there are but few will do any thing; therefore ſhall thoſe few do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? becauſe you meet with more reproach, then aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, therefore you will forbear acting for God! why, by the ſame reaſon, you may forbear praying in your families, and hearing of Sermons, for theſe things are ſubject to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach too.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52031:12"/>
            <p>But you do not know yet what to do, you apprehend more difficulty in theſe things, then you can at preſent foreſee, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs. — And ſo you alwayes will, till you are reſolved with chriſtian courage to bear down difficulties, to turn over objections to be anſwered by faith, to beg wiſdom of God by prayer, and to ſet down this with your ſelves, <hi>God offers me an opportunity of doing good, how ſhort it may be I know not: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be faithfull unto God, nor ſo much as anſwer it to mine own conſcience, if I do not trade my talent for my Maſters greateſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: I will therefore honour God with my ſubſtance: I will return him ſomething, that gave me all.</hi> Beloved, can you poſſibly rake up any demurre why you ſhould not lay out your ſelves to the utmoſt for God; which God may not infinitely return upon you, why he ſhould never have given Chriſt unto you? and why Chriſt ſhould never have undertaken your reconciliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God? can you meet with the difficulties Jeſus Chriſt met with? can you meet with that contradiction of ſinners, that Chriſt bore? He was not diſcouraged. He went up and down doing good. He left you an example, that you ſhould follow his ſteps. Be followers of Chriſt as dear children. If the example be too high, take <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> 2 Chron 31.21. <hi>in every work that he began in the ſervice of the houſe of God, and in the Law, and in the Commandements, to ſeek his God, he did it with all his heart, and proſpered.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
